The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Dear brothers and sisters,
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته’
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he would leave to go Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
he would appoint somebody behind to take care of the affairs of Madina and to take care of the affairs of his family.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ on this journey, the Battle of Tabook(تبوك),
he appointed Muhammad Ibn Muslima(محمد ابن مسلمه) to be the Ameer(امير) over Madina
and he appointed Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) to take care of his family.
Some of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) as usual they started spreading rumors around,
how come Rasool Allah ﷺ left Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) behind.?
They were saying; "اِسْتَثْقَلَهْ"
The literal meaning is, he is heavy, meaning he is a burden
and that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ left him behind.
So Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him,
I mean this is what people are saying and
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) wanted to go out obviously not to miss out on such as a Ghazwa(غزوة).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
یا علی : أمَا تَرْضَى أنْ تَكُونَ مِنِّي بمَنْزِلَةِ هَارُونَ، مِن مُوسَى، إِلَّا أنَّهُ لا نَبِيَّ بَعْدِي
O Ali(علي) doesn't it please you to be to me, what Haroon(هارون) was to Musa(موسى).
Except that there is no Prophet after me.
When Musa عليه السّلام went to speak to Allahعَزّوجَلّ, he left behind Haroon عليه السّلام
and he appointed him to take care of the affairs of Bani Israel(بني اسرائيل).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and I'm doing the same to you.
You are to me what Haroon(هارون) was to Musa عليه السّلام.
Except that there's no Prophet after me because Haroon(هارون) was a Prophet.
So, this is one of the great virtues of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
that we the people have Sunnah(سنة) believe in, obviously the Shia(شيعه) carry this too far.
And based on it, what cannot be based on this Hadith(حديث),
but we as Ahl-Us-Sunnah(اهل السنة) believe that
Rasool Allah ﷺ did leave Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) behind and this is an authentic narration.
And that Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) held a special status with Rasool Allahصلوات الله وسلام عليه,
and the army left.
Some of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) were speaking among themselves and they said;
Do you think that fighting the Romans is like Arabs fighting each other?
You're going to come back tied in ropes.
Speaking such words in an army that's going out to meet an enemy is not good
this is a demoralizing, it's not good to talk in such a way
and put fear in the hearts of the soldiers and terrify them, about their enemy.
And even though this conversation was private but  Allahعَزّوجَلّ exposed them to Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ammar Bin Yasir(عمار بن ياسر) go to those men
and ask them what they have said, because they have burned themselves.
"اِحْتَرَقوْا اَدْرِكْهُمْ"
Catch them because they have burned and ask them, what they have said.
If they do not admit it, tell them you have said so and so, you have said such and such.
So, Ammar Bin Yasir(عمار بن ياسر) went and told them that this is what you have said.
They came back to Rasool Allah ﷺ apologizing.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية),
وَلَئِنْ سَأَلْتَهُمْ لَيَقُولُنَّ إِنَّمَا كُنَّا نَخُوضُ وَنَلْعَبُ ۚ
When they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, they said, O Rasool Ullah, we were just joking.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَلَئِنْ سَأَلْتَهُمْ لَيَقُولُنَّ إِنَّمَا كُنَّا نَخُوضُ وَنَلْعَبُ
قُلْ أَبِاللَّهِ وَآيَاتِهِ وَرَسُولِهِ كُنْتُمْ تَسْتَهْزِئُونَ۝
لَا تَعْتَذِرُوا قَدْ كَفَرْتُمْ بَعْدَ إِيمَانِكُمْ
إِنْ نَعْفُ عَنْ طَائِفَةٍ مِنْكُمْ نُعَذِّبْ
نُعَذِّبْ طَائِفَةً بِأَنَّهُمْ كَانُوا مُجْرِمِينَ۝
And if you ask them, they will surely say we were only conversing and playing,
say is it Allah and His verses and His messenger that you were mocking, make no excuse.
You have disbelieved, after your belief, if you pardon one faction of you,
we will punish another faction because they were criminals.
And these are versus 65 and 66 of Surah Toubah(سورة التوبة).
These Ayaat(آيات), make it clear that joking and mocking anything of religious value is Haram(حرام)
and it can reach to the level of Kuffr(كفر).
Because Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
لَا تَعْتَذِرُوا قَدْ كَفَرْتُمْ بَعْدَ إِيمَانِكُمْ ۚ
Make no excuse you have disbelieved after your belief.
And if we look at it, what have they said,
They just said that the Romans are going to defeat you.
So, this tells us that mocking, making fun of anything in Islam,
whether it is making fun of Qur'an, making fun of Hadith(حديث),
making fun of Rasool Allah ﷺ or joking in a way that is disrespectful to the divinity of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
All of this is very, very dangerous and it can lead to Kuffr(كفر) and it's a sign of Nifaaq(نفاق).
So, we need to be very careful, and not make jokes and fun because
sometimes there are jokes that are inappropriate,
there are jokes that make fun of Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an or su'ar(سورۃ) of Qur'an
this should be avoided because of the extreme danger in it, it's blasphemy.
So, as a Muslim, we need to be very cautious.
It also tells us that Islam is sacred
and we have to hold it in high esteem and give it the sanctity that it deserves.
We should not belittle our religion and we should not let anyone else belittle our religion.
So, these stern warnings were to the Munafiqeen(منافقين),
who're making fun of the Muslims and the abilities of the Muslims.
And also today, if we could implement these meanings on our modern day,
even if we are weak, or disunited, we should not spread rumors and words that weaken the Muslims.
And we should not implant in the minds of the Muslims that your enemy is undefeatable
and that you are weak, and you have no hope and you have no future.
All of this, things that we should we as Muslim should not involve in,
and we need to uplift the Ummah(امة), we need to encourage the Ummah(امة),
we need to remind the Ummah(امة), that is,
كُنْتُمْ خَيْرَ أُمَّةٍ أُخْرِجَتْ لِلنَّاسِ
You are the best nation that was brought forth to mankind,
we need to remind the Ummah(امة) of its bright past and bright future also.
Because we do as Muslims have a bright future because the future belongs to the Muttaqeen(متقين).
وَالْعَاقِبَةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ
The end belongs to the people of Taqwa(تقوى).
So, we should not speak about the ability and the strength and the power of the Kuffaar(كفار)
and the weakness and the disunity of the Muslims in a sense that demoralizes the Muslims
and makes them give up and accept the status quo.
As a Muslims, we shouldn't do that.
Now, the army left and as we mentioned before,
Rasool Allah ﷺ made Istanfaar(إستنفار) a general mobilization.
Every Muslim everyone, who says, "لا اله الا الله" Needs to come out.
The army left and there were some people who stayed behind.
Now whenever they would come to Rasool Allah ﷺ and say
so and so did not come Rasool Allah ﷺ would say;
دَعُوْه’ ، فَإِنْ يَكُنْ فِيْهِ خَيْرٌ فَسَيَلْحِقْهُ اللهُ تعالى بِكُمْ ، وَإِنْ كَانَ غَيْرَ ذَلِكْ فَقَدْ أَرَاحَكُمُ اللهُ مِنْه’
Leave him alone, if there's any good in him, Allah will make him follow you.
And if he is not, then Allahعَزّوجَلّ has given you relief from him.
And then they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said: Abu Dhar(ابوذر) is not with us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said the same thing, Leave him if there is any good in him, he would follow you
and if not then Allah has relieved you from him.
Abu Dhar(ابوذر) was following them but his camel was slow and when it slowed him down too much,
he picked up his belongings and jumped off the camel and left.
And Abu Dhar(ابوذر) was walking in the desert, with his belongings, in the heat of the desert.
And then the Muslims see in the horizon, this man appearing far away
walking alone in the heat of the desert.
They came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said: O Rasool Ullah, there is a man following us, far away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
"كُنْ اَبَازَرْ"
Be Abu Dhar(ابو ذر).
When the man approached, it was Abu Dhar(ابو ذر).
So, they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said: O Rasool Ullah, it is Abu Dhar(ابو ذر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
يَرْحَمَ اللهُ أَبَا ذَرْ ، يَمْشِيْ وَحْدَه’ ، وَيَمُوْتَ وَحْدَه’ ، وَيُبْعَثُ وَحْدَهْ
May Allah have mercy on Abu Dhar(ابو ذر), he walks alone, will die alone,
and will be resurrected on the Day of Judgment alone.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), the years passed,
and Abu Dhar(ابوذر) was living in the time of the extreme wealth of the Muslims and the Muslim Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
And Abu Dhar(ابوذر) was a man, who was brought up in the tough desert,
who believed in Islam, in the early days, when things were still tough.
Abu Dhar(ابوذر) accepted Islam, when Rasool Allah ﷺ was in Makkah, when the things were hard.
And Abu Dhar(ابو ذر), his personality, his description was,
he was a very dark man, well built, huge and he was hot tempered.
And he was very strict, he was a very strict man.
And he was a Zahid(زاهد), he followed a strict form of austerity.
And he had the belief that Muslims should not store wealth, and keep it.
And that they should give their wealth to the needy, and in the causes of good.
While the predominant view among the Muslims
and this is the view that is adopted by the Ulema(علماء) is.
If a person pays a Zakat(زكواة) of his money than the rest of his money is Halal(حلال)
and people can save money and can leave behind money.
Otherwise, there would be no point in having laws of inheritance in Qur'an,
if you're not going to leave anything behind,
but Abu Dhar(ابوذر) used to follow this strict austerity
and he was not getting along with the authorities
and it was not getting along with many people.
He was in Ash-sham(الشام) in the time of Muawiya(معاويه).
And Ash-sham(الشام) was the store of the wealth, that was where the wealth is.
Ya'ani(يعني) because of the Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), with Romans
and because of the land of Ash-sham(الشام) itself is very blessed land,
the Muslims were becoming very wealthy over there and he was not happy with that.
So, Muawiya(معاويه) sent a letter to the Khalifah(خليفه) Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان)
because Muawiya(معاويه) was the governor of Ash-sham(الشام), he sent a letter to the Khalifah(خليفه) telling him
لَقَدْ اَفْسَدَ علَىَّ اَبُوْ ذرْ اَلشَّامْ
Abu Dhar(ابوذر) has ruined Ash-sham(الشام) for me.
So, Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) recalled Abu Dhar(ابوذر), and summoned him to come back to Madina.
So, Abu Dhar(ابوذر) left Ash-Sham(الشام) and he came to Madina.
And Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) told him to stay in Madina.
Abu Dhar(ابوذر) told Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان), I want nothing to do with your Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), leave me alone.
Allow me to go to Ar-Ribdah(الربداة),
which was a very small village or town and middle of the desert.
So, Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) gave him permission.
I mean, he didn't even want to stay in Madina, he was totally against what he was seeing.
So, Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) gave him permission to go to Ar-Ribdah(الربداة), he went there,
and that's where he lived.
And Uthman(عثمان) told him that I'm going to give you some camels as provision for you.
He said: I want nothing to do with them, I will survive on my own.
And he just left without taking anything.
And when he was on his deathbed, alone, in the middle of the desert,
with no one but his wife and no servant, no neighbors, no friends, no one.
And Abu Dhar(ابوذر), the companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ, this great Sahabi(صحابي), the scholar
he used to be a Mufti(مفتي) in the time of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), Umar(عمر) and Uthman(عثمان).
And now he's living alone no students, no friends, no neighbors, nobody.
And he's on his deathbed.
So, his wife started weeping.
He told her: Why are you crying?
She said: How come? You don't want me to cry,
when you are dying over here and I don't even have anything to use as your coffin.
And I have no strength and ability to burry to you.
He told her;
اَبْشِرِيْ وَلَا تَبْكيْ
Be happy and do not cry, because I heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say, to a gathering that included me
One of you, will die in Falah(فلاح), Falah(فلاح) is an empty land.
And his burial will be witnessed by a group of believers, Mo'mineen(مؤمنين).
And then Abu Dhar(ابوذر) said: And all of the people in that gathering died.
And the only one left behind is me.
And they have all died in Jam'ah(جماعة)
They were all in a group, I'm the only one that fulfills this Hadith(حديث), dying alone.
So,
اَبْصِرِ الطَّرِيْقْ
Go and check out the road.
She said: What road are you talking about, the Pilgrims have already left home,
they're back in their homes and the roads are unused.
So, probably this was an area, where pilgrims would pass through.
But after that you rarely see anyone, but he told her to go out.
So, she would go out spend some time watching, seeing if there's anybody showing up.
And then she would go back and nurse him,
until one day she saw a group of men riding on their camels coming from the horizon.
كَالرَّخُمْ
They were described as looking like vultures.
Apparently she gave them that description,
because probably if you're in a desert, and you see people coming from far away on camels,
that's how they would look like, like vultures.
So, she waved to them and they came to her and they told her,
what do you want Amat Ullah(اَمة الله), O servant of Allah! What is it that, you need?
She said: There's a man over here who's dying and I want you to take care of him.
They said: Who is he?
She said: Abu Dhar(ابوذر),
they said: The companion of Rasool Ullah.
She said: Yes.
فَفَدَّوْهُ بِآبَائِهِمْ وَاُمَّهَاتِهِمْ
They sacrifice their fathers and their mothers for him.
They said: May our fathers and mothers be sacrificed for him.
And they rushed to help Abu Dhar(ابوذر) and they came in,
when he was lying down in his last moments and he told him, Abshiroo(أبشرو)
I give you the glad tidings, Rasool Allah ﷺ told me that you will die in an empty land.
And your burial will be witnessed by people, who were believers.
And then he told them, if I or my wife had the garment that is suitable for me to use as a coffin,
I would've used it but I have nothing.
Abu Dhar(ابوذر) was living with nothing.
He was visited by Abu Musa(ابوموسى) once,
and Abu Musa(ابوموسى) came and saw Abu Dhar(ابوذر) doing this housework.
And he came in to help him and Abu Dhar(ابوذر) told him;
إلَيْكَ عَنِّيْ
Leave me alone.
Abu Musa(ابوموسى) said: I'm your brother,
Abu Dhar(ابوذر) told him you're not my brother,
you used to be my brother before you assume positions of leadership.
And he didn't even want to have anything to do with somebody, who was appointed as an Ameer(امير),
you can see how strict Abu Dhar(ابوذر) was, in his Zuhad(زهد).
And this other visitor came and described Abu Dhar(ابوذر)
as having an unkempt hair and very old garments, he is living a very difficult, hard life.
So, now it's time for his Janazah(جنازه) and he doesn't even have anything to use as a coffin.
And then he told them, he said: If I had anything or my wife had anything, I would have used it, but I don't have anything.
And then he told them and I don't want anyone of you to give me a coffin
if you have been an Ameer(امير) or a policeman or a postman.
So, if you have been an Ameer(امير) working with the government,
or a police officer or a postman I don't want you to give me anything.
So, if there is anyone among you, who hasn't assumed these posts in the past, then he can give me a coffin.
All of them have assumed these roles, one point of time, except one Ansaari(أنصاري)
who was a young man among them, who didn't.
And he said, I'm going to give you two garments that were made by my mother.
And he gave him that to use as his coffin, and Abu Dhar(ابوذر) died alone, and he was buried.
And they prayed the Janazah(جنازه) on him.
And this is the end of the life of one of the great Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Dear brothers or sisters, I mean, forget about following the way of Abu Dhar(ابوذر), no one of us could do that.
But we talked about Abu Dhar(ابوذر),
so that we can make a comparison with ourselves and see how miserable we are.
I mean, the luxury we live in, the safety, the security, the wealth, the easiness of life.
When we compare that to the way of Abu Dhar(ابوذر), who held on to the strict Zuhad(زهد) until he passed away,
it shows us the huge difference between us and him.
And it makes us realize how unfortunate we are.
We asked Allahعَزّوجَلّ to forgive us.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to guide us to the straight path and make us true believers.
Another one of the Sahabah(صحابه), an Ansari(انصاري), a man from Al-Ansaar(ألانصار),
his name is Abu Khaisamah(ابوخيثمة),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Muslims left he was still in Madina.
He went back home and he has two Areesh(عريش),
Areesh(عريش) is a hut made from tweaks.
And in summer when you pour this water on this hut,
it becomes very comfortable and cool inside because air can come through.
And when it's soaked with water, it's natural air condition.
So, he had these two huts and there was one of his wives in each hut
and they have prepared for him food and cold water.
So, he comes in and sees this.
And then he says;
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ـ فِيْ الضَّحِّ (الشمس) وَالرِّيْحِ وَالْحَرْ، وَأبُوْ خَيْثَمَةْ فِيْ ظِلِّ بَارِدْ
وَطَعَامِ مُهَيَّأ, وَاَمْرَأةٍ حَسَنَاءْ فِيْ مَالِهِ مُقِيْمَ؟ ؟!، مَا هَذَا بِالنَّصَف العدل،
ثٌمَّ قَالَ: وَاللهِ لَا أَدْخُلُ عَرِيْش وَاحَدَةٍ مِّنْكُمَا حَتَّى أَلْحَقَ بِرَسُوْلِ الله ـ صلى الله عليه وسلم ، فَهِيِّئَا لِيْ زَادًا
He said: Rasool Allah ﷺ is in the hot weather and the wind
and Abu Khaisamah(ابوخيثمة) is in a cool shade and a prepared food.
And with beautiful wife, this is not fair.
In the name of Allah, I'm not going to enter into any one of these huts,
until I follow Rasool Allah ﷺ, so prepare my provisions.
So, they prepared for him, his provisions and he pulled one of his camels, and he followed Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He only catched up with them when they were at Tabook(تبوك)
and he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
أَوْلَى لَكَ يَا ابا الْخَيْثَمَه
And that's a warning from Rasool Allah ﷺ to Abu Khaisamah(ابوخيثمة).
And then he told Rasool Allah ﷺ what happened,
So Rasool Allah ﷺ made Dua(دُعَا) for him.
Dear brothers and sisters reflection on this story of Abu Khaisamah(ابوخيثمة)
pretty much the way Abu Khaisamah(ابوخيثمة) saw things in Madina
is how we are and we are even in a better situation.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَا تَدْخُلُوا مَسَاكِنَ الَّذِينَ ظَلَمُوا أَنْفُسَهُمْ، إلَّا أَنْ تَكُونُوا بَاكِينَ
فَاِنْ لَمْ تَكُوْنُوْ بَاكِيْن فَلَا تَدْخُلُوْعَلَيْهِمْ ،( حَذَرًا)، أَنْ يُصِيبَكُمْ مِثْلُ ما أَصَابَهُمْ
Do not enter the dwellings of the people, who transgressed against themselves,
except if you are going to weep,
if you are not going to weep then do not enter their dwellings,
lest the punishment that afflicted them, afflicts you.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them to just pour away the water that they got,
and the dough that they made from that water, to feed it to the animals.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to have nothing to do with Samood(ثمود), or their land or their water.
Nothing! And Rasool Allah ﷺ told us why?
We should either take the reminder and the lesson and weep because of what happened to them.
Otherwise, we should stay away
because the punishment of Allah could befall us like it befell them.
And what we learn from this is, that
we should have no pride whatsoever with the so called civilizations of the past that were Mushrikeen(مشركين)
and who were punished by Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
How can we have pride in Babylon, and Firoun(فرعون) and all of these other Kuffar(كفار),
when they were enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ?
How can we be proud with the pyramids or proud with the ruins of Babel(بابل)
or the ruins that exist in other parts of the Muslim world, whether they are Roman or Greek or whatever,
when these were people who are Kuffar(كفار), who are enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
It's very sad to see Muslims having pride in their Pre-Islamic history.
And this is a plot by the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
By the way, they have mentioned this in some of their writings,
that we want to revive the pre Islamic history in order to attach the Muslims to it.
And this would lessen their attachment to their Islamic history.
We need to put things in the right perspective.
These are the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and we should not visit their sites
except if we are going to take the reminder from it and if it is going to soften our hearts
and make us weep because of the fate that occurred to them
because of the wrath of Allahعَزّوجَلّ on them because of their Kuffr(كفر).
Nowadays, it is a shame to see some Muslims taking these photographs next to the mummy of Firaoun(فرعون),
while they're smiling and happy.
It is a shame to see that some Muslims are going as far as even naming their sons Firaoun(فرعون),
having pride in that part of history to the extent that they would name their sons Firaoun(فرعون)
and this is because of this reviving, and they called civilizations.
And they call it civilizations in a good sense, when in reality they have no civilization at all.
Rasool Allah ﷺ went to make Wudhuu(وضؤ) and he was very late for Salah(صلاة).
So the Muslims made Iqamah(إقامه) and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) led the Salah(صلاة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ catch them, while they were still in prayer.
And Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) wanted to retreat but Rasool Allah ﷺ had him carry on
and Rasool Allah ﷺ prayed behind Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف)
that makes Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) the only Sahabi(صحابي), whom Rasool Allah ﷺ prayed behind him.
And this is a great virtue for Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه.
Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه, says, that in the middle of the night, during the Battle of Tabook(تبوك)
I saw a torch so I followed it and I saw Rasool Allah ﷺ, Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and Umar(عمر)
and Abdullah Zul Bajadain Al-Muzni(عبد الله ذوالبجادين ألمزني) has died and they have prepared his grave
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was the one, who descended into his grave,
while Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عمر) were the ones, who were descending the body to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah was telling them bring down your brother
and they were handing Rasool Allah ﷺ the body of Zulbajadain(ذوالبجادين).
Zulbajadain(ذوالبجادين) was a very poor man, unknown, simple
and it was Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عمر) and Rasool Allah ﷺ himself, who were preparing his Janazah(جنازه)
and Abdullah Bin Masood(عبد الله بن مسعود) was watching
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ was the one, who put him with his own hands in the grave
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَللَّهُمَّ اِنِّيْ قَدْ اَمْسَيْتُ رَاضِيًّا عَنْهُ فَارض عَنْهُ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: O Allah I am pleased with him, so O Allah be pleased with him.
Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه said;
يَا لَيْتَنِيْ كُنْتُ صَاحِبَ الْحُفْرَهْ
I wish that I was the one, in that grave.
To have this blessing of Rasool Allah ﷺ making that Dua(دُعَا) for you
and holding you with his hands and putting you in the grave is such a great blessing.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبد الله بن مسعود) said: I wish I was there.
When the army reached to the land of Romans, Ash-Sham(الشام),
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to Uqaidar(اُكَيدر), Domat Jandal(دومة الجندل),
the king of Domat Jandal(دومة الجندل).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to bring him to capture him and bring him.
And Uqaidar(اُكَيدر) was living in a very strong fortress in Domat Jandal(دومة الجندل).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ told Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), you would find him hunting bulls,
you find him hunting, Uqaidar(اُكَيدر) used to go and hunt.
And he would go out on horseback with a large group of his men
and they'd travel and spend extended periods of time searching for the bulls.
I mean, it wasn't an easy thing and he used to train his horses specifically for that.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), with a number of Muslims to capture him and bring him.
And it was a full moon night.
And Uqaidar(اُكَيدر) was with his wife, on his roof, roof of his palace.
And Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), they saw the bulls come right to the gates of the fortress,
and they were scratching their horns on the walls, or on the gates of the fort.
And that is something unbelievable, they have never seen that before.
I mean, he would have to travel long distance to find them and here they are, right next to him.
So, his wife told him, Did you ever see anything like this?
He said: Never.
She said: Is this something that you could pass on?
He said: No.
And he immediately went down and told his servants to prepare his horses.
And he took with him a few of his followers along with his brother,
and they rushed out of the fortress to hunt down these bulls.
And they were routed by Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and they were surrounded
and the brother of Uqaidar(اُكَيدر) fought and he was killed.
And Uqaidar(اُكَيدر) and the rest surrendered.
And they were captured by Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
And they were brought to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he agreed to the terms of paying Jizyah(جزيه) and going back.
There was no fighting that occurred.
Because the Romans, when they heard about the advance of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allah has put fear in their hearts.
So, Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) they didn't come forth,
even though they had better preparation, large numbers, stronger weapons,
but they were afraid to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ in actual battle,
and therefore Rasool Allah ﷺ stayed there and waited for them, and nobody came.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ during that time, he opened a few cities
and made agreements with others, and took Jizyah(جزيه) from them.
So, it was very successful Ghazwa(غزوة), even though no fighting was involved.
It was very difficult it was a test for the Muslims as we have mentioned.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
لَقَدْ تَابَ اللَّهُ عَلَى النَّبِيِّ وَالْمُهَاجِرِينَ وَالْأَنْصَارِ الَّذِينَ اتَّبَعُوهُ فِي سَاعَةِ الْعُسْرَةِ
الَّذِينَ اتَّبَعُوهُ فِي سَاعَةِ الْعُسْرَةِ مِنْ بَعْدِ
مِنْ بَعْدِ مَا كَادَ يَزِيغُ قُلُوبُ فَرِيقٍ مِنْهُمْ ثُمَّ تَابَ عَلَيْهِمْ ۚ
إِنَّهُ بِهِمْ رَءُوفٌ رَحِيمٌ۝
Allah has already forgiven the Prophet and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين), and the Ansaar(أنْصَار),
who followed him in the hour of difficulty.
The hour of difficulty is, the Battle of Tabook(تبوك),
after the hearts of a party of them had almost inclined to doubt, because of the difficulty,
and then He forgave them.
Indeed, He was to them kind and merciful.
So, now you can see that we're reaching into the closing chapters
because forgiveness is something that comes towards the end.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ is being told and the Muslims are being told
that Allah has forgiven Rasool Ullah and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين), and the Ansaar(أنْصَار),
who followed him in the hour of difficulty.
So, Allah has given them Toubah(توبه), and has accepted their Toubah(توبه)
and this means that the end of the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ was approaching
because that is something that we do towards the end of Ibadah(عبادة) is to ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ for Istaghfaar(إستغفار).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ left from Madina initially, he was invited to pray in a Masjid(مسجد) that was newly built,
there were some people next to Madina, who built a new Masjid(مسجد), it was all done finished
and when Rasool Allah ﷺ was going to Tabook(تبوك),
they told him we want you to come and bless the Masjid(مسجد) with a Salah(صلاة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
I am traveling at the moment when I come back In Sha Allah(إن شاءالله) I will pray in your Masjid(مسجد).
But now we're traveling.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was close to Madina,
Rasool Allah ﷺ was informed about the true intentions of the people of this Masjid(مسجد).
You see, there was a man called Abu Aamir Al-Fasiq(ابوعامر الفاسق),
this man belong to Al-Khazraj(الخزرج) and he was a prominent member of the tribe.
He was given the name Abu Aamir Ar-Rahib(ابو عامر الراهب) in the time of  Jahilliyah(جاهليه),
because he was a believer in Allah and he used to worship Allah
and he has learned from the people of the book and followed their religion
and he was a very religious person, deeply devoted individual.
But Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), When Rasool Allah ﷺ came to Madina, he was one of his worst enemies.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), you can see the irony here of this devote individual,
a person who's deeply religious, you would expect him to be the closest to Islam,
but Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) he was the furthest.
You can also see the irony of Mushrikeen(مشركين), polytheists, they're becoming Muslim,
while the Jews and the Christians who know about Allah
and you would expect them to become Muslim, they didn't.
So, he went to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) encouraging them to fight against the Muslims
and he participated in the battles of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) against Muhammadﷺ.
In fact, in the battle of Uhud(أحد) he was the one who dug holes, the traps
in which Rasool Allah ﷺ, fell into one of them, which caused the teeth of Rasool Ullah to break
and for some iron nails from his helmet to enter into His cheeks.
This was caused because of Abu Aamir Al-Fasiq(ابوعامر الفاسق), his name was Abu Aamir Ar-Rahib(ابو عامر الراهب),
Abu Aamir(ابوعامر), the priest, he was given that nickname because of his, him being religious.
Rasool Allah ﷺ called him Abu Aamir Al-Fasiq(ابوعامر الفاسق),
Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) the corrupt rather than the priest, the corrupt.
When he saw that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were unsuccessful in their fight against Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he went all the way to meet Heracul(هراقل), Heraculus,
and he would ask him to send an army to invade Madina.
He was promised by Heracul(هراقل) that he would be given assistance.
And he used to send letters, Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) would send letters to some of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) in Madina,
promising them that I'm going to come with an army to destroy the Muslim state.
And what happened was, he asked them to establish a base from which they can spread their conspiracy,
a place where they can meet and plot and that place was the Masjid(مسجد), they built.
A Masjid(مسجد) gives them a good cover.
But in reality, it was a place to plot against the Muslims.
It was a place to promote the agenda of the Kuffar(كفار).
Rasool Allah ﷺ was given Wahii(وحي), revelation that exposed this plan.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in verse 107 to 109 Surat Taubah(سورة التوبه).
وَالَّذِينَ اتَّخَذُوا مَسْجِدًا ضِرَارًا وَكُفْرًا وَتَفْرِيقًا بَيْنَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ
وَتَفْرِيقًا بَيْنَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ وَإِرْصَادًا لِمَنْ حَارَبَ اللَّهَ وَرَسُولَهُ مِنْ قَبْلُ
وَلَيَحْلِفُنَّ إِنْ أَرَدْنَا إِلَّا الْحُسْنَىٰ ۖ وَاللَّهُ يَشْهَدُ إِنَّهُمْ لَكَاذِبُونَ۝
And there are those hypocrites,
who took for themselves a mosque for causing harm, and disbelief and division among the believers
and as a station for whoever had wared against Allah and His Messenger before.
And they will surely swear, we intended only the best.
And Allah testifies that indeed they are liars.
لَا تَقُمْ فِيهِ أَبَدًا ۚ لَمَسْجِدٌ أُسِّسَ عَلَى التَّقْوَىٰ مِنْ أَوَّلِ يَوْمٍ أَحَقُّ أَنْ تَقُومَ فِيهِ
فِيهِ رِجَالٌ يُحِبُّونَ أَنْ يَتَطَهَّرُوا ۚ وَاللَّهُ يُحِبُّ الْمُطَّهِّرِينَ۝
Do not stand for prayer there, within it ever.
A Mosque founded on righteousness from the first day is more worthy for you to stand in.
This is referring to the Masjid(مسجد) of Al-Qubaa(القباء).
Within it are men, who love to purify themselves and Allah loves those, who purify themselves.
So, Allah is telling Rasool Allah ﷺ, we should not pray in this Masjid(مسجد).
But you should pray in a Masjid that was established on Taqwa(تقوى) from the first day,
and where there are believers, people who want to purify themselves.
أَفَمَنْ أَسَّسَ بُنْيَانَهُ عَلَىٰ تَقْوَىٰ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَرِضْوَانٍ خَيْرٌ أ
خَيْرٌ أَمْ مَنْ أَسَّسَ بُنْيَانَهُ عَلَىٰ شَفَا جُرُفٍ هَارٍ فَانْهَارَ بِهِ
فَانْهَارَ بِهِ فِي نَارِ جَهَنَّمَ ۗ وَاللَّهُ لَا يَهْدِي الْقَوْمَ الظَّالِمِينَ۝
Then is one, who laid the foundation of his building on righteousness
with fear from Allah and seeking His approval better
or one, who has laid the foundation of his building on the edge of a bank about to collapse.
So, it collapsed with him into the fire of hell.
And Allah does not guide the wrongdoing people.
لَا يَزَالُ بُنْيَانُهُمُ الَّذِي بَنَوْا رِيبَةً فِي قُلُوبِهِمْ إِلَّا
إِلَّا أَنْ تَقَطَّعَ قُلُوبُهُمْ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
Their building which they built, will not cease to be a cause of skepticism in their hearts
until their hearts are stopped and Allah is Knowing and Wise.
Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that the Masjid(مسجد) should be burned down to the ground.
And that is what happened and the plot was exposed.
Brothers and sisters, the story of Masjid-e-Dharar(مسجد الضرار) is a story of a Masjid(مسجد)
that was established to promote Kuffr(كفر) rather than Eeman(ايمان).
While the Masjid(مسجد) of Qubaa(قباء) and the Masjid(مسجد) of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Madina
was a Masjid(مسجد) that was established from the first day to promote the truth.
And therefore, any Masjid(مسجد) that is existing today to promote the agenda of the disbelievers is a Masjid(مسجد) of Dharaar(ضرار).
And it is the same because Rasool Allah ﷺ was told by Allahعزَوجل.
"ضِرَارًا وَكُفْرًا"
It is a Masjid(مسجد) that was built, Dharaar(ضرار) which is harm and disbelief.
And this is something that occurs nowadays you find that there are Masajid(مساجد)
that promote the agenda of the Kuffar(كفار).
Rasool Allah ﷺ entered into Madina and he was greeted by the people, saying,
طَلَعَ الْبَدْرُ عَلَيْنَا مِنْ ثَنِيَّاتِ الْوِدَاعِ
وَجَبَ الشُّكْرُ عَلَيْنَا مَا دَعَى لِلَّهِ دَاعِ
Some historians mentioned that these words were said;
When Rasool Allah ﷺ, made Hijrah(هجرة) from Makkah to Madina,
but Ibn Qayyim(ابن القيم) says that, that is incorrect,
because Saniya Al-Widaa(ثنية الوداع) is to the north of Madina,
and when Rasool Allah would come from Makkah, he would be coming from the south.
Therefore, he says that this happened, when Rasool Allah ﷺ was coming back from Tabook(تبوك)
and not when he made Hijrah(هجرة) from Makkah to Madina.
Ibn Al-Qayyim(ابن القيم) then goes on to mention some lessons and benefits
that can be derived from this Ghazwah(غزوة).
There's one more incident that occurred in this Ghazwah(غزوة).
And I would mention that in the lecture of its own,
and that is the story of Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب إبن مالك).
So, we'll leave that In Sha Allah(إن شاءالله) to the next lecture.
We'll talk about some of the benefits
that were mentioned by Ibn Al-Qayyim(ابن قيم) in his book Zaad Al-Ma'ad(ذاد المعاد).
He says;
فَصَلْ: فِي الْاِشَارَةْ اِلَى بَعْضُ مَا تَضَمَّنَتْه’ هَذَا لْغَزُوْة مِنَ الْفِقْهِ وَالْفَوَائِدْ
A chapter on some of the benefits, we can learn in this as Ghazwah(غزوة).
He says;
اِذَاسْتَنْفِرَالْاِمَامُ الْجَيْشَ لَزِمَهُمُ النَّفِيْرَ
If the Imam(اِمَام) mobilizes the army, then it is a must on them to respond.
And he says;
اِنَّ الْاِمَامَ اِذَاسْتَنْفَرَالْجَيْشَ، لَزِمَهُمُ النَّفِيْر، وَلَمْ يَجُزْلِاَحَدٍ التَّخَلُّفْ اِلَّا بِاِذْنِهْ
If the Imam(اِمَام) mobilizes the army,
than it is mandatory on them to come and no one can stay behind.
وَلَا يَشْتَرِطْ فِيْ وُجُوْبِ النَّفِيْر تَعْيِيْنُ كُلُّ وَاحِدْ
And he says that a general mobilization is sufficient to make it obligatory,
he doesn't have to mention each one by name.
And then he says;
وَهَذَا اَحَدٌ الْمَوَاضِعِ الثَّلَاثَةْ اَلَّتِيْ يَصِيْرَ فِيْهَا الْجِهَادُ فَرْضِ عَيْنَ
And this is one of the three situations where Jihad(جهاد) becomes mandatory.
He said: The second is when the enemy invades the Muslim land
and the third is when the two armies meet.
The next benefit,
وُجُوْبُ الْجِهَادِ بِالْمَالْ
It is mandatory to support fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) with wealth.
He says;
وُجُوْبُ الْجِهَادِ بِالْمَالْ كَمَا يَجِبُ بِالنَّفْسِ وَهَذَا اَحْدِيْ الرَّوَايَتَيْنْ عَنْ اَحْمَدْ، وَهِيَّ الصَّوَابْ اَلَّذِيْ لَا رَيْبَ فِيْهِ
And he said, and this is one of the two narrations from Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) and he said;
there is no doubt in this, that it is mandatory to support fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) with your wealth.
And he says that it is more important than fighting with yourself.
جِهَادْ بِالْمَالْ شَقِيْقُ الْاَمْرِ وَاَهَمْ وَآكَدْ مِنَ الْجِهَادِ النَّفْسْ
And then he mentions the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
whoever finances a fighter than he has fought.
And he goes to mention that whoever has financial ability, then that is what he should do.
لَا يُعْذَرْ اَنْ الّعَاجِزْ بِمَالِهَ حَتَّى يَبْذُلَ جُهْدَهْ
He said: The one who is incapable of fighting is not excuse, until he does his best.
Because he said that the ones who stayed behind, they tried their best
they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, they said support us, finance us, we want to go out and they were eagerly trying to do so.
Because when they were told that Rasool Ullah has nothing to support you with,
they left with tears flowing from his eyes.
So, he said that you need to do your best.
لَا يَجُوْزُ الشُّرْبُ،وَلَا الطبخ ، وَلَاالْعَجْنُ ، وَلَاالطَّهَارَةْ ، مِنَ الْآبَارَ الثَّمُوْدْ
He said: It is not allowed to drink or cook or prepare the dough
or make Wadhoo(وضؤ) from the wells of the Samood(ثمود).
And he said, that the reason is, and he mentioned it in another situation.
It is because they are people whom Allah has incurred His wrath upon.
وَمِنْهَا اَنَّ مَنْ مَرَّ بِدِيَارِ الْمَغْضُوْبِ عَلَيْهِمْ وَالْمُعَذِّبِيْنَ
لَمْ يَنْبَغِ لَه’ اَنْ يَدْخُلَهَا وَلَا يُقِيْمُ بِهَا، بَلْ يُسْرِعْ اُلسَّيْرْ، وَيَتَقَنَّعْ بِثَوْبِهِ حَتَّى يُجَاوِزْهَا
He says: When you pass next to the places or the dwellings of the people
whom Allah has punished, then you should not enter it and you should not stay there,
and you should try to pass by it as fast as possible,
and you should cover your face with your clothes until you pass it by.
I mean, you should try to avoid it, as much as possible.
Except if you are going to enter it crying, and you learn the lessons.
جَوَازُ الْجَمْعَ بَيْنَ الصَّلَاتَيْنَ فِيْ السَّفَرْ
It is allowed to combine prayers in travel
because Rasool Allah ﷺ combined, when he was going to Tabook(تبوك).
اِذَا بَعَثَ الْاِمَامُ سَرِيَةً فَغَنِمَتْ كَانَ مَا حَصَلَ مِنْ ذَالِكَ لَهَا بَعْدَ تَخْمِيْسَهْ
If the Imam(اِمَام) sends, if the leader of the army sends a small group
and they have won some spoils of war, then what they have won is belongs to them,
after they give 20% of it, to the Ameer(أمير) of the Muslims,
according to the rules of Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
So, he says that it is not distributed among all of the army
but it is given to the ones, who were sent out.
فَصَلْ تحْرِيْقَ وَاَمْكِنَةِ الْمَعْصِيَّةِ وَهَدْمِهَا
Places of sin should be burned down.
And the evidence for that is what Rasool Allah ﷺ did with the Masjid(مسجد) Of Dharrar(ضرار).
He said: This is a Masjid(مسجد) where people are going to pray and mentioned the name of Allah.
Nevertheless, Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Sahabah(صحابه) to burn it, to the ground.
He said: What about the places of sin?
And he mentions like the places of prostitution and where alcohol is being sold.
And he gives them example.
He says, that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) has ordered that a village be burned down because they were selling alcohol.
So, these are some of the lessons that Ibn Qayyim(إبن القيم) has mentioned, from Ghazwa-e-Tabook(غزوة التبوك).
In sha Allah Ta'ala(إن شاء الله تعالى) In our next session we'll talk about the story of Ka'ab Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه.
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته